Guide to the Walter and Margaret Tong Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Walter and Margaret Tong Papers
1923-1972
RG 189
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Detailed correspondence and reports document American missionary work in the Philippines and Taiwan. Walter and Margaret Tong were missionaries serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Davao, Mindanao, Philippine Islands from 1931 to 1947. Following World War II Walter served as Candidate Secretary of the ABCFM and later they worked with Church World Service in Taiwan.
Tong, Walter
Tong, Margaret
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Tong family.
Biographical / Historical
Walter Tong was born in New Haven, Connecticut, the son of Mr. and Mrs. Henry Charles Tong. He received a B.S. degree from the Connecticut Agricultural College in 1928 and a B.D. from Yale Divinity School in 1931. Margaret (Peg) Whitfield Tong was born in Knowlton, New Jersey, the daughter of Mrs. and Mrs. Richard Whitfield. She graduated from Drexel Institute in Philadelphia, where she majored in home economics.
The Tongs served under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Davao, Mindanao, Philippine Islands from 1931 to 1947. Walter had oversight of ABCFM work in Mindanao, including the Davao Mission Hospital. In 1941, the Tongs were interned by the Japanese in separate camps - Walter alone, and Margaret with their three children, Eloise, Curtis,and Annarae. They were reunited in 1944 but remained interned until American forces liberated them in 1945. After the War, Walter returned to Davao to help in relief and reconstruction work.
In 1948, Walter was appointed Candidate Secretary for the ABCFM, a position he held until joining Church World Service in 1956 as a representative of the Congregational Christian Churches in Taiwan. In Taiwan, Margaret taught English and cultural skills to Chinese students recommended for study in the United States. Following their return from Taiwan, Walter returned to administrative work with the United Church Board for World Ministries (former ABCFM).
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Materials
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
The first section of Series I, Correspondence, consists of detailed letters written by the Tongs to family members in the United States while they were serving in the Philippines and Taiwan. These letters provide a good overview of their mission work and family life. The second section of Series I consists of letters written by Walter to his wife and children when he was in the Philippines and they were in the United States following World War II. Davao was devastated during the war and Walter was involved in re-establishing the mission work. These letters provide good documentation of the post-War situation in the Philippines. The third section of Series I contains non-family correspondence to and from the Tongs. Many of these letters are to/from colleagues in the Philippines, and to/from the central office of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. The final section of Series I, Circular Letters, includes circular letters of the Tongs and of other missionaries, which provide a good summary of their work.
The Writings and Notes of Series II are primarily those of Walter and Peg Tong. They provide additional documentation regarding their missionary work in the Philippines. The Collected Materials of Series III include detailed field reports of ABCFM mission work in the Philippines. Also included in this Series are materials related to Peg Tong's work with the Committee on Christian Literature for Women and Children in the Mission Field. The archives of this Committee are contained in YDSL Record Group No. 90. Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia includes programs and memorabilia from the Philippines and Taiwan as well as biographical information related to the Tongs.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Materials
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Missions -- Philippines; Missionaries; Tong, Margaret; Tong, Walter; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- Philippines
- Correspondence, Series I
  - To extended family in the US
    - Trip to Philippines and from Davao, 1931 Oct - 1932 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From Davao, 1933 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From Davao, 1933 Jul - 1935 Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From Davao, 1939 Aug- 1940 Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - From Davao, 1941 Jan-Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - From Taipei, Taiwan; from dedication of Brokenshire Hospital, 1957-1958; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Walter to Peg, children, family in US
    - From Manila, Davao, 1946 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - From Davao, 1946 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - From Davao, 1946 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From Davao, 1947 Jan- Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - From Davao, 1947 May-Sep (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - To/from others
    - A - B; incl. Herbert Brokenshire, M.D., Elton W. Brown, 1934-1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - C - H; incl. Chinese students of Margaret, 1945-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - J - M; incl. K. S. Latourette, Effa and Frank Laubach, James McKinley, Fred Moore (Director of Church Committee for Relief in Asia), 1932-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - O-S; incl. the Sexons, re. Davao Mission Hospital / Brokenshire Memorial Hospital, 1945-1951, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - T-Y, unidentified; incl. from Frank Woodward, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Misc. Filipino friends and colleagues, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - To/from ABCFM re. mission work in Philippines, 1923-1947 (Box 2, Folder 18-22)
    - To/from ABCFM re. mission work in Philippines; while Walter was in ABCFM administration; decision to work for Church World Service, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Misc. correspondence not to/from Tongs, re. mission work, 1933-1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Circular letters
    - Tongs, 1932-1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Other missionary colleagues B - K, 1946-1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Other missionary colleagues M - W, 1948-1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Writings and Notes, Series II
  - Incl. re. Davao, Christmas in the Philippines, Dr. Herbert Brokenshire, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Notes for talks and prayers, 1945-1958, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Notes, quotations, poems, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Notes for talks, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Biographical essay re. Norman Thomas, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Collected Material, Series III
  - ABCFM Philippines Mission
    - Field reports incl. Evangelistic work at Lanao, Cagayan, Davao, Silliman Bible School, Cagayan Mission Hospital, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Field reports incl. Mission schools, Northern Mindanao, Ebenezer Girls' Dormitory; Davao, Lanao, Agriculture - Baliangao, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Field reports incl. Literacy campaign, Davao, Silliman Bible School, Dansalan station, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Field reports incl. Davao, Lanao, Ebenezer, Silliman Bible School, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Field reports incl. Davao, Curth Memorial Hall, Cagayan Hospital, Silliman, Lanao, North Mindanao, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Field reports incl. Ebenezer, Nursery (trees) work in Dansalan, Lanao, Maranaw Folk School, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Personal reports: Tong, Laubach, Woodward, and others, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Annual meeting minutes - Philippine Mission, incl. standing rules, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Annual meeting minutes - Philippine Mission, incl. joint meeting UEC Executive Committee, Missionaries, and Boards deputation, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Annual meeting minutes - Philippine Mission incld. Mindanao Inter-conference council meeting, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Financial reports - Davao Hospital; Missions treasurer, 1927, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Financial reports - incl. Cagayan Hospital, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Financial reports - incl. Cagayan Hospital, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Financial reports, 1948, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous statistics - Davao, Lanao, 1931-1933 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Other material
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Taiwan Church World Service, 1950-1971 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - News clippings (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Committee on Christian Literature for Women and Children in the Mission Field
    - By-laws, Committee reports, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Budgets and minutes, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Annual and semi-annual meeting reports, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Annual meeting, bubdets, book lists, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Lit-Lit Newsletters and other printed material, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Programs, postcards (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Regarding work at Davao Hospital, Cagayan Hospital, Silliman Bible College (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Memorial service for Dr. Herbert C. Brokenshire, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Taiwan memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Biographical material: WT's Commission in Army reserves (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Biographical material: Commissioning as missionaries: news clippings, etc. (Box 3, Folder 63)